<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reasons vvhy this kingdome ought to adhere to the Parliament.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 26 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92297</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R592</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E108_30</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16010</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859953</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859953</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112057</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92297)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112057)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 19:E108[30])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Reasons vvhy this kingdome ought to adhere to the Parliament.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "August 1st 1642".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:112057:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>REASONS VVHY THIS KINGDOME ought to adhere to the <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ow ſoone doe men forget the by-gon time of their affliction? or if they retaine a darke and miſty remembrance of the time paſt, they want the diſcretion by comparing it with the time preſent to foreſee and prevent evill times to come. And this ſeemes to be now the condition of us the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of England, who have almoſt forgot how our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, Lawes, liberties, and properties in our eſtates lay bleeding almoſt to death at the feete of a Malignant partie of Papiſts, Prelates, and Court Prieſts, Innova<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Councellors, corrupt Judges, with their depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, Petty-Foggers, Solicitors, Projectors, Monopoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, and other Prerogative Paraſites: How unjuſt and deſtructive a warre was projected by the ſaid Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants betweene us and our brother Nation of <hi>Scotland?</hi> wherein we were ſure, if we were conquered, to looſe our ſelves and all we had to the Conqueror with whom we fought; and if wee did conquer, to the Malignant partie for whom we fought: How (to ſecure our bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage)
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:112057:2"/>the old Engliſh Souldiary of Proteſtants being disbanded in <hi>Ireland,</hi> an Army of 8000. <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts, (the conductors at this day of the bloody rebellion there) were raiſed by <hi>Strafford,</hi> and kept hovering over our heads, ready to fall upon us (weakned with an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy conqueſt) and to lay that Iron yoke upon our neckes to which we ſhould unworthily have ſubdued our brethren.</p>
            <p>But what our oppreſſions and grievances were in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, who were the Authors, what aymes they had, and what meanes they uſed, how farre they proceeded before this Parliament, and ſince; what the faithfull en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours of this Parliament are, and what they have done already for us, and at how little a charge, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the great burdens and ſlavery they have freed us from, what dangerous oppoſitions, attempts, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes (diſtructive to the being of Parliaments and to their owne perſons) they have (through the goodneſſe of God) overcome, and are ſtill environed withall: How faithfully to our benefit they have disburſed the publike money, and upon what juſt, neceſſary, legall grounds, and with what reſpect to the King and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome they have managed all our affaires. How (as Chriſt was led aſide into the Wilderneſſe to bee temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) his Majeſtie is led aſide from his great Councell the Parliament (in whom there is ſtrength) into a Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe of errors and weakneſſes: And what the points of difference betweene his Majeſtie and the Parliament are at this time. He that is capable of ſatisfaction, and deſires withall to know what ſhare he is likely to have in the publike calamities (if not prevented) and how to carry himſelfe therein, let him reade the third Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance, the ſeverall Declarations, the generall accounts of the Kingdome publiſhed by the Parliament, together with thoſe moſt excellent Obſervations; the one upon
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:112057:2"/>his Majeſties anſwer to the Lords and Commons of the 19. of <hi>May,</hi> 1642. The other upon ſome of his Majeſties late Anſwers and Expreſſes.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe the Anſwer to the <hi>Sommer ſet ſhire</hi> Petition, and a good plaine Paper, called Some more new Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations concerning King and Parliament, containing 20. conſiderations. Another Paper intituled Jeſuits plots: And a Paper called a ſhort diſcourſe tending to pacification of differences betweene his Majeſtie and his Parliament; where theſe truthes appeare as cleare as the Sunne, in deſpight of Envy and her blacke mouth'd daughter, Slaunder, which alwayes attends good deeds in a bad age, as the ſhadow attends the body.</p>
            <p>But that after ſo many prayers and petitions to God for a Parliament, we ſhould ſo much forget his mercies, our owne ſufferings and complaints, and the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments faithfull, wiſe, and effectuall indeavours, as to hearken to the voyce of a Malignant party, who flatter us, calumniate them, and abuſe all; this ſheweth us to be the Sons of <hi>Adam,</hi> apt to be tempted, even with an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. But let us examine the cauſes of this our incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy and ingratitude, which may be partly inward in our ſelves, and partly outward in others.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Inward in our ſelves, as,
<list>
                  <item>Firſt, long diſcontinuance of Parliaments hath filled this Kingdome ſo full of diſeaſes, that we grow weary of Phyſicke before our Phyſitians can perfect the cure, and had rather venture a relapſe then confirme our healthes by ſtirring up more humours.</item>
                  <item>Secondly, becauſe the Parliament did not ſeaſonably ſatisfie our anger with puniſhment of Delinquents, wee are now tired with expectation, and as angry with the. Parliament as with Delinquents. But if wee conſider how, and by whom they are protected, where they take
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:112057:3"/>Sanctuary: and how the multitude of offenders, their friends and abetters is ſuch, that—<hi>Hos defendit nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, junctoque umbone phalanges;</hi> They are too many, too ſtrong to be brought to puniſhment, unleſſe the Parliament found more abilitie in themſelves and more conſtancy in the people then they have yet met withall, the Parliament is to be excuſed.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly outward cauſes of our unconſtancy and ingratitude proceeds from the ſubtiltie and induſtry of the malignant partie; who with all dilligence in their reports, diſcourſes, writings and publications, nay in Churches and Pulpits ſet faire gloſſes upon their owne fowle actions, and with foule paintings, ſtaine the faire merits of the Parliament. Let us exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine ſome of their calumnies, for all is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the Malignants obſerving us to bee freed from painefull Symptomes, and willing to take our reſt and eaſe (upon the advantage of our ſloath) perſwade us to take this for a cure (though the diſeaſe lie yet lurking in our Bowells) and to grow angry with, and ſuſpiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of our Phiſitians, as if they kept us in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary courſe of Phyſicke to continue their power and government over us. But their delaies proceeded partly from the throng of great and weightie buſineſſes, which (like waves continually falling in one upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) hinder themſelves in the crowd; And principally from the ſlights of the Malignants.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the Malignants object, that this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is a burden to the Common-wealth, that they free us from Taxations of Shillings, by impoſitions of Pounds, by Subſidies, Polemoney, Loanes, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Firſt, In deſperate diſeaſes (ſuch as the Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants had infected this Common-wealth withall) Blood-letting is neceſſary, the veines will fill againe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:112057:3"/>if the vitall parts be preſerved; if wee contribute part of our particular wealth to free the Common-wealth from ſlavery and ſuperſtition (the parents of repining ſloath and dejected Cowardiſe) wee ſhall incourage in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, and renew our ſtocke: but if wee ſtoope un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der an Arbitrary government, who will worke that others may devoure the fruits of his labours? Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie is the fountaine of induſtry, &amp; induſtry of wealth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Beſides, the Parliament hath already payd us liberally for all the Taxes they have made us pay; and our payments are but for the preſent; their bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits and good Lawes are perpetuall. The aboliſhing of ſuperſtition and reforming our Religion. The vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicating our Lawes, Liberties and Properties are ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimable. Shipmoney did yearely coſt the kingdome above 200000. pound, Coate and Conduct mony, and other military charges (beſides the trouble and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour) almoſt as much. A few Monopolies did yearely prejudice the Subject a Million. Sope 100000. pound, Wine 300000. pound, Leather almoſt 400000. pound, Salt 400000. pound; all theſe, with many other Monopolies this Parliament hath taken away. Beſides what infinite dammage thoſe diſcouragements of trade brought inviſibly upon the Common-wealth, as well <hi>Lucro ceſſante,</hi> as <hi>Damno emergente.</hi> And (which is the benefit of all benefits, the Quinteſſence, the Elixer, the ſpirit extracted out of all their indeavours) the roote of all theſe wrongs is declared to be againſt law by an Act of Parliament, being an arbitrary power, which (for their owne benefit more then his Majeſties) the prerogative paraſites pretended to be in the King) of taxing the Subjects &amp; charging their eſtates at pleaſure, without limitation, and without conſent in Parliament.</p>
            <p n="3">3. This Parliament had not beene ſo chargeable to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:112057:4"/>the kingdome, had not the Malignant partie continually multiplyed their troubles, charges and dangers, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarded the remedies.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, this Parliament is more hated then any for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Parliament hath beene: Firſt, becauſe it hath found more Delinquents, and hath gone farther in ſearching and curing wounds and diſeaſes, and eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a perfect reformation both in Church and State, then ever any did. Long intermiſſion of Parliaments having filled this Common-wealth ſo univerſally with ill humours, that (in this old doting age, wherein it drawes to its period) wee can neither indure its diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, nor the remedies. And herein this Parliament is moſt unhappy. Secondly, becauſe it cannot be broken without their owne conſent: Ever ſince which act paſt, all wayes have beene taken by the Court faction, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve or deſtroy it; before thoſe quarrells about <hi>Hull</hi> or the <hi>Militia</hi> were thought of.</p>
            <p>All which plots fayling, they now attempt (what no age will ever beleeve, unleſſe it be as wicked as this) to render odious and ſuſpected to the people this onely Sanctuary of their Religion, Lawes, Liberties, and properties. The repreſentative body of the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, they labour to make this and all other Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments invalid and of no authoritie or reputation with the people, by infuſing ſuch opinions and doctrines into them as are inconſiſtent with the nature of Parliaments, and will ſtrike dead the very roote of them, if they bee generally believed. Firſt, that if the King deſert the Parliament, it is a voyd aſſembly, and without power to defend the kingdome, even from open violence. A Right, not denied to a private perſon aſſaulted. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that Parliament priviledges are no where to be read,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:112057:4"/>and ſo the Repreſentation of this whole kingdome gives them no priviledge nor authoritie. Thirdly, that the major part in Parliament is not conſiderable, when ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are abſent or diſſent. But to ſtay untill all, or almoſt all are preſent and aſſenting, and not to <hi>acquieſſe,</hi> in the Majoritie, is never to bring any thing to concluſion, nay to bring all to tumults and confuſion. Fourthly, that the major part is no major part, becauſe the fraud of ſome few miſleads them. This Poſition divides the Parliament into two unworthy ſorts of men, Deceivers, and Deceived. Fiftly, that Parliaments may doe diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable, nay treaſonable Acts. And that this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath beene ſo blinded by ſome few Malignants, as to abet Treaſon in Sir <hi>John Hotham.</hi> (Anſwer to the 19. Propoſitions <hi>p.</hi> 2. See the Anſwer to the Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration <hi>May</hi> 26. <hi>p.</hi> 1. 2. 11. and 28. 29.) Here you ſee Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon charged upon the repreſentative body of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and conſequently, by reflection, upon the whole body of the kingdome repreſented. If therefore his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie take Armes, it muſt be againſt us all (Parliament and People) involved in one common crime of Treaſon. And yet the maxime of the law is, that no diſhonorable thing is to be preſumed of Parliaments. And (I believe) neither reaſon, nor example can ſhew any thing againſt this rule. Sixtly, that the Parliament hath trampled upon all Law, and the Kings Prerogative, &amp; ſought to inſlave the whole Kingdome. During the long abſence of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the Prerogative had ſwallowed the Law, which this Parliament cauſed to be vomited up againe, and reſtored to the people, when the Malignant partie thought it had beene digeſted and converted into the very nature of the Prerogative. And this is one dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous effect of the long want of Parliaments, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever the Prerogative devoures, though it digeſt and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:112057:5"/>incorporate not with it, but breake forth into Wens and other unwholeſome excretions; yet (becauſe they are of ſome continuance) both Prince and people, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially evill Counſellors (who onely thrive by the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe of exorbitant power) take it for a part and mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Prerogative, and make it a matter of ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall and quarrell, that after ſo long a ſufferance, the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament ſhould launce or pare away thoſe tumors. But that the Parliament (ſo ſmall a body armed onely with a derivative power of repreſentation, having an Active Anti-parliamentary faction of Monarchiſts in the heart of it, and which hath beene put to labour for its preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation ever ſince the Bill paſſed for perpetuating of it) ſhould trample upon the Law, and inſlave the whole kingdome, ſeemes wonderfull; it being the onely foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and foundation of our Lawes, the Sanctuary whither the people flie for ſuccour when they are op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in their Lawes, Liberties, and Properties; and which ſo lately hath redeemed the People and all they can call theirs, out of bondage, and the members there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of being ſure to ſuffer amongſt the multitude, whenſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver our Lawes faile us. Seventhly, that the Parliament ſought the betraying of Church and State; and to effect the ſame, had erected a new upſtart authoritie in the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litia,</hi> and levied warre upon the King. They may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly be ſaid to betray Church and State; who corrupt the doctrine and diſcipline in the one, and ſubvert the Lawes and forme of government in the other. And if any man be ſo great a ſtranger in our <hi>Iſrael</hi> as not to know who they are, I will tell him. Firſt, the Prelates, and Court Prieſts brought many alterations into our Liturgy and Rubrick (contrary to the Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whereby the Common Prayer booke is eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) vaine Ceremonies, Altars, and many new doctrines
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:112057:5"/>into our Church (to make us more conſonant to the Church of <hi>Rome</hi>) as Epiſcopacy and Tithes, <hi>Jure Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vino.</hi> That the King hath a Divine Prerogative pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramount to all our Lawes. That the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is a true Church and erres not in fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talls (and then wee are Schiſmatickes at leaſt) That Auricular confeſſion is of neceſſitie, &amp;c. Theſe are a few of their corruptions in Doctrine: Diſcipline followes: They inlarged their juriſdiction againſt Law. The High Commiſſion uſed the Temporall Sword by fining, impriſoning, as well as the ſpirituall. They uſed an independent juriſdiction, not derived from the King (which they claimed <hi>Jure Divino</hi>) in their owne name, and under their owne ſeales, contrary to the Stat. <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>C.</hi> 17. 1. <hi>Ed.</hi> 6. <hi>C.</hi> 2. ſtill in force: In the State, The attempts of the Malignant partie to ſubvert our Lawes, Liberties, and Properties, and to reduce this well tempered Monarchy into a meere Arbitrary Government have beene ſufficiently proved in the tryall and attainder of the Earle of <hi>Strafford;</hi> yet I will not omit the teſtimony of the Lord of <hi>Faulkland,</hi> who wittily tells us: The King was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded by his Divines, that in conſcience, his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellors, that in Policy, and his Judges, that by Law hee might doe what hee liſt: And if this bee not a conſpiracy to, introduce Arbitrary Government, and change our State, I know not what is.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Militia,</hi> they deſire not to remove it from the King, but from his ſubordinate Miniſters, and place it upon other Miniſters whom they ſuſpect not; and to ſatisfie the feares of a whole Nation in time of danger, is wiſedome. Beſides, extraordinary diſeaſes require extraordinary cures; the High diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:112057:6"/>and dangers of the Kingdome compells the Parliament (That ſupreame Court and Counſell now deſerted by the King) to have recourſe to the ſupreame Law, <hi>Salus populi;</hi> Whoſe immediate riſe is from the Law of Nature, which teacheth every worme, much more a man, and moſt of all a whole Nation to provide for its defence.</p>
            <p>Beſides, it neither belongs to the perſon, nor calling of the King to expound the Lawes: But that the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament hath a power to declare Law without the Kings conſent, nay, againſt it, (though not to make it without him) is apparent; for all inferiour Courts have the ſame. And what Counſellors and Interpreters of the Law his Majeſty hath now about him, to be put in bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance with the faith and learning of a whole Parliament? What Expoſitions of Lawes and Stat. they have made, Let his late publications and Commiſſion of Array, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the petition of Right, and their opinions and judgements given ſince that was enacted upon Ship-mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, <hi>Habeas corpora, &amp;c.</hi> teſtifie. 8ly. That <hi>Parliaments</hi> cannot declare Law, but in particular Caſes, legally brought before them. It ſhould ſeeme by this, that <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments</hi> have no Conuſance of Cauſes, but upon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints <hi>ab extra:</hi> But the Houſe of Commons, being the great Enqueſt of the Kingdome, may, and ought to take Conuſance of Cauſes, of publique concernment, <hi>ex officio:</hi> and is accounted miſconuſant of nothing. 9ly. That <hi>Parliaments</hi> are queſtionable and triable elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where. The <hi>Parliament</hi> is the ſupreame Court, and hath the laſt appeale; Anciently errors in other Courts were tryed there: Therefore no other Court can have Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuſance
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:112057:6"/>of their Actions nor perſons; which were to appeale ridiculouſly, upwards and downwards. And if a <hi>Parliament</hi> be triable and arraignable before the King himſelfe: Then hath the King an unlimited declarative power of Law above all Courts, in his own breaſt; and the laſt Appeale muſt be to his diſcretion and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and conſequently, the Legiſlative power His alone. And yet his Majeſty is pleaſed to confeſſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe not skilfull in the Lawes. I know no third tryall to which a <hi>Parliament</hi> can be liable, unleſſe it be the triall by the Sword: from which, and from thoſe that coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell it, the God of Battels defend us; and grant us cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage to defend our ſelves. (Theſe laſt recited) Doctrines and poſitions have received Anſwers of another nature at large, In the Obſervations upon his Majeſties laſt <hi>Anſwers</hi> and <hi>Expreſſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. But the <hi>Bug-beare</hi> which workes moſt upon the people, is, Leaſt theſe differences betweene his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty and <hi>Parliament</hi> ſhould entangle us in a civill War. It ſeemes they have little beliefe in his Majeſties prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations and imprecations, to governe peaceably and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally, who feare this: and they leſſe faith, who threaten them with it. But take heed you doe not draw on a War, by fearing it: Courage is the beſt Antidote a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it.</p>
            <p>Wherefore I ſhall admoniſh you, that no War can be more deſtructive to you, and all that is yours, then your owne Cowardiſe, if it ſhould ſo far fright you from your conſtancy, faith, and gratitude, as to make you deſert this <hi>Parliament:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For,</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:112057:7"/>
Firſt, you cannot forſake this Parliament, and leave it to the mercy of the Malignants, but you ſhall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake your ſelves, and your Religion, Lawes, Liberties, and properties open to the ſpoyle and oppreſſion of an Arbitrary Government (more remedileſſe and not leſſe waſting then a warre.) And either have no more Parliaments (for, when they may take what they liſt you ſhall never be called to give) or (if by vertue of your trianniall Act) there ſhould bee another Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſummoned, what faith and courage can you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from ſuch Members as muſt either offer up your Lawes, Liberties and properties that ſent them, or (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſtitute of your Protection) become themſelves a Sacrifice? Such a ſlaviſh Parliament will lay the ſure foundation of all our ſlaveries: For as our Lawes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect us and all that is ours, and Parliaments protect our Lawes, ſo we muſt protect them and their priviledges from violence. Next conſider how forraigne king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes are governed, where (for want of Parliaments) the will of the Prince and his Favorites is the Law of the People. And how this kingdome was gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned during the long intermiſſion (when honeſt men were out of hope, and knaves out of feare) of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments?</p>
            <p>Secondly, He that thinkes a Parliament can be forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, knowes not the power of Parliaments; for if the Parliament pleaſe to imitate your unconſtancy &amp; faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe cowardiſe, and, deſerting your intereſt, purſue on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly their own, and comply with the King, They are able to doe him more ſervice in one week, then <hi>Joſeph</hi> did to <hi>Pharaoh</hi> in twice ſeven yeares. They can make him more abſolute then any Prince in Chriſtendome, nay
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:112057:7"/>then the Turk or Muſcovite. They can repeale all the good Laws they have got for you: They can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive the Star-Chamber, High-Commiſſion, &amp;c. and ſet the Pillory upon your neckes, and little <hi>Laud</hi> upon your eares againe: They can bring in and naturalize the Exciſes of the Low-Countries, the Gabels of France, the Alcavales of Spaine, and all the Taxes of Florence, and make England the Map of all the oppreſſions in the world, they can give away your Laws, Liberties, and Properties by a Statute, and eſtabliſh a perpetuall Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny by a Law, which ſhall ſtop your mouthes for ever, when you ſhall be told that the Act of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative body is the Act of the whole Kingdome, and you are bound by the Lawes of the Land; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints againſt illegall Taxes ſhall then no more bee heard in your Streetes for want of Lawes. Neither think this plot ſo ſhallow, that the members of this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or their poſterity ſhall draw in the ſame yoke with you: No, they may entaile their ſeverall Votes and Seats in this already perpetuated Parliament to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their heires Males for ever: And (as the Fable ſaith, that the Lion proclaiming a generall day of hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, all beaſts of prey waited upon him for their ſhares) ſo theſe may have a ſubordinate ſhare, according to their ſeverall capacities, in your ſpoiles and booties. The L. Treaſurer <hi>Burleigh</hi> was wont to ſay, <hi>He knew not what a Parliament could not doe;</hi> And truly I know not what a Parliament (concurring with his Majeſty) cannot be. They may be the only favourites and Privadoes, and ſtrike all others into the Boxe, and lie in their roomes. Biſhops ſhall not ſtraine their Conſciences nor braines to invent a Theologicall engine, called a Divine Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:112057:8"/>for battering your Laws, Liberties, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties; the Votes of the Parliament ſhall ſhake them in ſunder: They ſhall be the Kings Cavaliers, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due you and all yours (feare not a Civill War) without blow ſtriken, and with a moſt permanent victory. And this whole Kingdome ſhall conſiſt only of a King, a Parliament, and Slaves. What King will reject ſuch ſervants, or neglect ſuch a <hi>Compendium</hi> of power and profit upon any conditions? Miſtake me not: I doe not ſay or thinke they will doe this, they have ſhewed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves more pious, juſt, faithfull, then to deſerve ſuch a ſuſpition. But take heed you doe not cancell the obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion your election hath laid upon them, by an undeſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, ignoble miſtruſt: Many a man hath provoked his wiſe to lewdneſſe, by thinking her lewde; Teach them not by your example to be, what you would not have them to be: If either indignation or feare ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare their mindes to make a politique uſe of your faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe cowardiſe; what might not they get, and you loſe? Who will not rather forſake then be forſaken, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice himſelfe for the ſafety of a company of ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, unfaithfull cowards? Honour is the reward of vertuous actions, and protection is due to them who protect your Religion, Lawes, Liberties, and Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Give it them for their ſakes and your owne, or blame them not if they follow the dictates of nature, and provide for their owne ſafety, by deſerting you who would deliver up them. Be true to your ſelves, that they may be true to you; for who will ſtick to him that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandons himſelfe? Let not feare betray thoſe helpes which reaſon offers you. And God ſend us all mindes prepared for peace, hearts fit for War, and no cauſe to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:112057:8"/>uſe our hands in ſuch a ſervice: yet if ſo ſad an occaſion doe come, let us meet it with the manly alacrity of Chriſtians; Knowing that all things worke together for the beſt to them that love God. I conclude with <hi>Seneca, Leve eſt quod ferre poſſum; Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve eſt quod ferre non poſſum.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
